All right, so today we're going to be looking at
two instructional paintings by
Yoko.
Oh no, that I tried to translate into code.
The first one is called a
painting to see the skies and the instructions from 1961,
summer of 1961, are
drill two holes into a canvas,
hang it where you can see the sky,
then in
parentheses.
Change the place of hanging.
Try both the front and the rear windows
to see if the skies are different.
And we'll look at the project first and then we'll
look at both projects and we'll look at the code.
So here's our canvas.
And
by clicking on it, we drill two holes.
And then we hang it where we can see the sky.
And this is some video of a sky that I've slowed down.
I feel like I'm going to be able to see the sky.
And then we found it on the internet archive.
And then when we click it a third time,
we tried both the front and rear windows
to see if the skies are different.
And that's it.
That's the whole thing.
I will run it one more time.
The other piece,
voice piece for soprano,
has the instructions that are also visible in the piece here.
Scream,
one against the wind,
two against the wall, and three against the sky.
And this one is from Autumn of 1961. And in this one,
we have an audio element here.
It's two seconds long.
It is the Wilhelm scream,
which I encourage you to read the
Wikipedia page of or look at the letter,
letter box collection of several hundred movies that included
this particular scream.
And we have three buttons here that apply different
convolver nodes to the audio element.
And we'll talk a little bit more about what
convolver nodes are and what convolution reverb is.
But this is,
this is how I translated this piece.
So. Three really different specializations of
the Wilhelm scream.
So we can look at some code for.
Painting to see the skies.
We have basic HTML boilerplate here.
I used a comment to include the poem itself.
And then in the head,
we have some CSS. This is a video container
stuff that I have used in other tutorials,
including the one with the plant,
where it slows down in a loop.
Just kind of,
how do we get the video to full screen?
And then layer something on top of it.
In this case, the canvas.
So we have the video container,
which is full with full height of the viewport.
We have the video itself,
which covers the entire.
Frame of the container.
And we have the opacity set to zero with a transition,
which lets the,
lets it fade in fairly quickly,
but gradually.
Then we have this canvas element,
which is the canvas for the painting,
which is 20% from the top and left.
It has a border doesn't need to.
We could make a fancy.
We could actually have a frame on the canvas if we wanted.
And then.
This transition, I believe,
is for the flip.
It is.
This color shift doesn't need to be here,
because it's,
that's from the plant thing,
I think.
No, no,
it doesn't need to be here.
It's for the backdrop filter.
That changes the color as seen through the element,
but not of the element itself.
So filter.
We've talked about a little bit.
You know, you can add
Gaussian Blurs,
you can change the saturation,
you can make things gray scale.
You can change.
Hue rotation.
You can change a number of kind of visual color
effects of of any CSS element using the filter.
And backdrop filter takes the same arguments,
but only affects things beneath the element that you're looking at.
So you can have, like, clear text in an element.
And then we have the element that you can see.
And then blur everything that's behind it.
It's,
it's useful when you're using layers.
So. Then we have HTML. We have the container as the outer element.
We have the video inside,
which auto plays muted and loop.
If the video had sound,
it would probably provoke.
The need for.
Permission to do auto play.
But since there's no sound,
and because it's muted.
And just play as a background element.
We then have the canvas also in the video container with
a with the 400 by 300. Canvas elements again require.
Within height,
because as there are kind of image that.
If it isn't specified,
it doesn't.
Like it, there isn't an image that,
you know, like of a.
It doesn't bring in its own coordinate system.
It doesn't bring it to its own dimension.
So you have to set them.
And then I've got this textive that isn't being used.
So we're pointing video in the script here.
To the video element.
This is the sky is setting the playback rate to half.
Because it just looks nicer.
And it also loops unevenly.
So slowing it down means that won't happen as often.
Then we're setting the get context.
On the canvas element, which lets us.
Do operations.
On the canvas,
we're filling it with this tan color.
If we had done that with CSS,
then we wouldn't actually be able to punch holes in it.
And. I'll remind you that these these drawing
functions are very similar to what exists within p5.js.
P5.js has its own native circle function.
Tough as script is not.
So the way that I'm drawing the circles
is a little bit more complicated than.
So I would work in p5.js.
But this is this is how it goes.
So I have a thing that tracks the number of
clicks to decide what instruction to follow.
And then each time the canvas is clicked,
it iterates this clicks variable.
So the first one will be one.
I'm
dumping it to the console log so I can kind of see what's going on.
And if clicks is less than or equals to two,
then.
This is how we draw.
So I'm using this to get the x,
y coordinates of where the mouse
clicked relative to the canvas element.
So you can see here.
Normally, when I do a click event,
these parentheses would be empty like
like this.
In this case, I'm passing the event.
As a variable into the function that follows.
And so E here.
Has a
property that.
The the DOM object of the target in
which in this case is the canvas element.
We could just as easily say,
can here.
But it's a good habit to actually be
able to pass this from the function.
And then use.
Because you could potentially have
this event listener to multiple items,
things like that.
So using the E is a it's a good thing to know how to do.
So in this case,
we're looking at the target and we're getting
the client bounding rectangle and subtracting.
It's locate it's like x,
y coordinates from the x,
y coordinates of the mouse that gives us a relative position of
the mouse clicks relative to the object that's being clicked.
And then.
We begin a path and I'm using the
path of the circle as a clipping path.
So that I can erase only the contents of the circles
and make them transparent.
This is the the perforation of like the drilling through.
So we begin a path.
Don't know.
I don't remember why is that the fill style of the black.
I don't think it matters.
Here we have the save online 93 and the restore on 98. That is
basically equivalent to p5js is push and pop where you're setting.
Kind of settings of an object.
That you're then resetting.
And so in this case,
it's the being able to.
Set.
The path
as a clip.
Dimensions for for clipping and then being able to reset them.
So. This circle is set as a new path
to D. And then this arc is the circle.
It's the coordinates.
Because it has a diameter 40 and the it's going to.
I'm trying to correct for centering it.
Because otherwise it would be in the corner.
And then it's like two times a math times pi gives us the circle.
This is just you can look at the MDN documentation for
arc to get kind of more advice about how to use this.
So then we set the clipping path to the circle.
And then we clear the entire contents
of the canvas of the rectangle that is,
you know,
from the 0 0 of the upper left hand corner to its width and height.
And then the path is only going to clear what's inside that
even though we're giving the direction to clear the entire thing.
And so that is that is how you set that up.
So that runs twice.
If you were to just set the clipping path
and then like not do this even restore thing,
it would only it would only work once because the path was set.
If clicks is three,
it brings the video style opacity up.
And then if it's more.
than that, it
adds this flip.
And the flip is performed by using the transform function.
There's also translate functions that let you specify degrees.
It's flipping on the y-axis.
There's a few different ways to do this
in CSS. But this was the cleanest way.
And that's the whole program.
That's then look at voice piece for soprano.
There's very little CSS on this.
There's just a button,
which I made larger than the default in
the HTML. There is the audio controls.
Wilhelm MP3. Then I'd header this as scream and three buttons.
And you can see here that I used the
on click attribute inside the element.
This is equivalent to doing.
In JavaScript, like
adding an event listener to click.
And you can also add.
You could also,
there are about three different ways to do this.
But this seemed like a nice poetic way to have scream,
and scream wall,
scream sky in the in the element.
Of the button so that,
you know,
when you view source,
you see it this way.
Also to give you different different ways of doing the same thing.
Similar to the canvas context, which is the
JavaScript access to really being
able to do operations on the canvas.
As opposed to the DOM element,
the audio context is the equivalent of that for audio.
And the audio context has kind of a different ontology.
It has like the system of inputs and outputs.
Starting with,
in this case,
the source is the audio audio element.
On the page, this here with Wilhelm.mp3.
And I have to connect that through an
intermediary node and then connect that to the,
to the destination.
And the destination is the,
the browser that allows it to connect to the
operating system and eventually your speaker.
So in this case, the function of scream,
which is being passed here by the,
by the button with the argument,
either sky wall or wind.
I can also imagine screaming into the cloud,
which could be an interesting project.
But it sets up the system where it's,
it's checking the,
the type of,
of this context where,
right here,
it's set,
it's just setting up the scope here.
And right now, the type of audio context,
as we run through the program linearly,
would be undefined,
because it hasn't been set yet.
It's not set until down here.
So the first time the function runs,
it gets set.
So it's looking at the type of of this thing.
And if it's an object,
if it's been set as an,
as an audio context,
then it makes sure that it's not set.
It's sort of closed the audio context,
which kind of resets it to its resets anything that's been set in it.
And I had to do this because once you add the reverb,
you add the,
the Convalver node,
adding another Convalver node,
changing the Convalver node doesn't seem to work.
So this was sort of like a reset of the audio context.
But if it's still undefined, it's not set.
It doesn't need to do this.
So audio context is set as a new context.
And setting it as a new context does not,
apparently,
erase its earlier settings.
So that's, again, the need for the close here.
And then we set audio to the audio element source
is this create element media element source,
which is setting the context to.
connect to the audio
tag as opposed to using,
you know, there's other nodes like
oscillation nodes where you're creating
sine waves or square waves or sawtooth
waves that you are synthesizing audio from from
from anywhere or from a stream
there's different kinds of source nodes
that you could have besides the audio
element on the page
and then we're creating this reverb based on the
location that's getting passed so wind wall or
sky is then being passed to this other function
and then we're connecting the reverb to the source
and then we're connecting the destination to the reverb
so it's kind of a straight line if you've worked
in audio and you've ever had a patch bay or you know
kind of like
you know connecting your MP3 player to an
amplifier which then has speakers it's kind of the
same metaphor then as part of the screen function it sets the
current time of the audio to the beginning to zero and then plays it.
There are different ways you could do this where it actually
made a new audio element for each reverb thing and then
kind of layered them on top of each other as you hit the
buttons that would be kind of neat but this is kind of a
this is just how I did it quickly.
So let's look at this create reverb function
it gets passed the location sky or wall or
wind and
then it creates the Convalver and this is a
method on audio context this is the kind of
one of the many kinds of nodes that you can create.
Convalver is an intermediary node where you're passing
something through it it acts as a filter there also panning
nodes that will let you kind of create a new audio element.
There are some interesting things you can do where
you know based on the mouse position you could
pan things you know like dynamic interactive audio.
There are gain nodes that let you make things
more or less loud.
There are a few different kinds.
And the way that Convalver nodes work are generally
a wave file of what's called an impulse recording.
And impulse recordings there are few different nodes that are in the same way as the one that you can see.
There are different kinds.
In these cases they are capturing the reverb of a
space it's a loud noise that's played into a space
and you essentially get kind of the long tail of
how that sound you know reverberates.
And so if you took a starter pistol into a cathedral and recorded
the sound of it firing and the full kind of duration of how it works.
So it's a long way to get silent that would be an impulse response.
People also use these to make profiles of different amplifiers.
If you play guitar contemporary amplifiers we'll have all
of these settings to simulate a martial stack or to simulate
an old tube amp from the 60s or 70s. Same process but a
slightly different approach.
Because those impulse response recordings tend to be very short.
People collect these.
You can
get them online.
There are some repositories that have free ones.
There are some repositories that really
want to sell you them for a lot of money.
I got these from a collection on the York University in Canada.
So these are all from Canada.
And so this one I found on the Internet archive the one I used for
wind is actually taken from a recording audio recording of the moon.
That somebody processed in a way that was like oh like
this is a historical recording that was
not meant as an impulse response but
they were able to do some
some math on it.
And there isn't really wind on the moon.
So maybe this wasn't the best one for me to
use but I thought it I thought it worked.
And then the law one is in this empty warehouse in Canada.
Very reverberant.
And then this one is in a park during the summertime.
Coli National Park in Canada.
Where it's a shorter impulse response because you're outside
there are fewer surfaces for the sound of reverberant against.
And so what it does is it fetches this file and
then it loads it into an array buffer which is a
very special kind of array for audio signals where
you know you have many many digits after a decimal
point that a normal array would not be able to hold.
When you're working with audio you need to work with it.
Work with these spectral buffers and you decode
the audio data into the convolver and return it.
And this took some trial error an error on my part working
with examples from Mozilla where they had this you
know this cow bouncing around on a screen and different
convolver nodes that made it reverberant in space.
And so I don't expect you to know how
to do this just you know like you know.
Naturally in your own brain you have to look to examples
and documentation and Web Audio is very complicated.
There will be a future tutorial that shows how to use
some of the libraries that make this easier to work with.
But this is how I threw this together.
And that's how that works.
So it runs this function.
It returns the convolver to this create reverb thing.
And then it's just able to connect it as a node.
And so
that's how that works.
So you can go find
other
convolver nodes on this open air hosted York site.
I encourage you to go check that out.
If you want to try to add some like atmospheric
audio to an interactive thing you're working with.
Thanks
for hanging in there.